Guide to the Cai Yongchun Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Cai Yongchun Papers
1924-2018
RG 205
Yale University Divinity School Library
6.75
(16 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, and research materials by and about Cai Yongchun (Ts'ai Yung-ch'un) (1904-1983), provide insight into the life and work of a Chinese scholar, educator, and theologian, and into conditions in China during the Cultural Revolution.
Cai, Yongchun, 1904-1983
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Joan Hongyu & Dorothy Liangyu Cai, 2006
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Cai Yongchun (Ts'ai Yung-ch'un) was born of Christian parents on March 16, 1904 in Jinjing near Xiamen (Amoy) in South Fujian (Fukien) province. He attended Yenching University but became ill with tuberculosis, and was compelled to return to Fujian for treatment. He was in Hungling Hospital from September 1926 to January 1927. By July 1928, Cai had moved to Guangzhou (Canton) for his health and continued his studies at Lingnan University. In September 1929, he returned to Yenching to study sociology, and wrote a thesis on China's population that won him election to Phi Tau Phi and Phi Beta Kappa. While at Yenching he assisted missionary Dorothy Barbour in writing two books. He continued his studies at Yenching School of Religion. During 1936-1938 Cai and his wife Huang Xiuying (Hsiu ying) were back in Fujian where he taught Church History and the life of Jesus, while she taught Psychology at Minnan (also known as South Fujian) Theological College in Xiamen (Amoy). In 1938, Cai was imprisoned by the Japanese for a time and when Xiamen (Amoy) was occupied by the Japanese, the Cai family retired to Xuiying's family home in Hong Kong, and they served on the faculty of Canton Union Theological College. From 1937 to 1939, ten million Chinese migrated westward to escape Japanese rule and the ravaging of Shanghai, Nanjing, and Guangzhou. The Canton Theological College joined the trek to Yunnan. Cai, though also teaching at the Seminary and Central China College, took on as his main work initiating a mission among the Petso people, called by Han Chinese Minzhia (Min chia) in the valley from Dali northward and in the surrounding hills. A sociologist as well as a missionary, Cai was able to make a script for Minzhia, for the first time, he believed. Cai's health prevented him from going with the seminary when it moved back to northern Guangdong province.
From 1942 to 1943, Cai was Lecturer for the Church of Christ in China in their Kunming church. He then accepted the post of chaplain at the Church Missionary Society's Huidian Hospital in Kunming. Cai was still in Kunming in 1946, when a letter came from T. C. Chao, inviting him to teach Comparative Religion at the newly reconstituted Yenching School of Religion, and to prepare himself for it by study in England or America. Cai studied at Columbia University and Union Seminary in New York City during 1946-1947. Cai's M.A. thesis was written in the same academic year under Reischauer and Rev. R. H. L. Slater of Cambridge University on "Tali Funeral Rites: Study in 'Ancestor Worship' and his degree was granted in May 1947. He received his Ph.D. from Columbia University in 1950. Cai returned to China but his plans to teach at the Yenching School of Religion were disrupted by the Communist takeover. He was unemployed for four years, 1952 to 1956. During this time he translated several books and papers at home, including China Belongs to God. From 1956 to 1961 he taught at Northeastern Peoples' University in Changchun, Jilin. In the winter of 1969, after the Zhen bao incident on China's northeast border with Russia Jilin faculty was dispersed into the countryside. The Cais were sent to Helong, a village of 100 families in Kirin province, near the Korean border, where life was very arduous. He later returned to Jilin and officially retired in 1975. In 1978 he began to edit and compile an anthology of New Testament passages, which was published only in 1992 after his death. In 1979, Cai was publicly rehabilitated and reinstated as professor in Jilin, from which he returned in 1980 to live with his daughter in Tianjin and Beijing. He died in 1983.
For more detailed biographical information see Ts'ai Yung-chu'un's Life and Work: Fully Chinese and Fully Christian, by Hugh Barbour, Yale Divinity School Library Occasional Publication No. 14.
Scope and Contents
The writings and correspondence in this collection provide insight into Cai Yongchun's life and work and into conditions in China during the Cultural Revolution. Much of the material is in Chinese. The documents in Series ! through VI were organized and described by Michael Poon of Trinity Theological College and given to the Yale Divinity School Library by request of Cai's daughters in 2006. Cai and his wife were close friends of the George and Dorothy Barbour family and the Barbour's son Hugh wrote a biographical sketch of Cai, published by the Yale Divinity School Library in 2000. Series VII, added in 2010, consists of materials collected by Hugh Barbour in preparation for writing his biography of Cai, Ts'ai Yung-chu'un's Life and Work: Fully Chinese and Fully Christian.
Arrangement
I. Writings and Notes of Cai Yongchun, 1930-1987
II. Biographical Documentation, 1945-1985
III. Correspondence, 1925-1997
IV. Writings about Cai Yongchun, 1983-2002
V. Personal Items and Memorabilia, n.d.
VI. Materials of Huang Xiuying (wife), 1931-1996
VII. Research Files of Hugh Barbour, 1924-2002
- Writings and Notes of Cai Yongchun, 1930-1987; Series I
  - Writings in English
    - A.1.1.1-1 "Population & Livelihood in China", 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Thesis submitted to the faculty of the College of Applied Social Sciences of Yenching University as a partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Bachelor of Arts. This thesis won the Phi Beta Kappa award.
    - A.1.1.1-2 "Population & Livelihood in China", 1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      The original typed version: i-iii Introduction; iv-v Contents; P.1-P.118 Photocopy from the Beijing University (Yenching) Library.(only P.1-P.118)
    - "Tali Funeral Rites—A Study in 'Ancestor Worship'", 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Thesis submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of Arts in Columbia University under the faculty of Union Theological Seminary, New York, 1947 *Original Typed Copy and *Photocopy: Acknowledgements; Contents (4 pages); P.1 Introduction - P.59 (final)
    - A.1.1.3 "The Philosophy of Ch'eng I - A Selection of Texts from the Complete Works Edited and Translated with Introduction and Notes ", 1950 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
      Dissertation submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in the Faculty of Philosophy, Columbia University. *Original typed copy: An Abstract; iii-viii Contents; ix-x Preface xi-xiii signs, Abbreviations and Explanatory Notes; P.1- P.376
    - The Philosophy of Ch'eng I - published version of Ph.D. dissertation, from China Academic Library series published by Springer, 2018 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - A.1.1.3.1 Dissertation: files of the work progress: 1) 考试及考证：二程全书版本（14页） 汇刻书目、卷九（4页） Cheng I and Aristotle (18 pages) Specific amendments suggested by the Examining committee of the dissertation on Cheng I by Mr. Ts'ai (14 pages) 零纸（像书目）（ 2张） 2） 二程哲学书目：书目、已译完书目、书籍评阅、版本等 （共四个栏目 74页） (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - A.1.1.3.1 Dissertation: files of the work progress: 3） Revised MS Introduction & Chap.1 Only (P.1- P.86) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - A.1.1.3.1 Dissertation: files of the work progress: 4) 制订程颐研究纲目（经过） 秀英贴条（Xiuying's Note）:"美国博士论文在战前一律要求印刷成书分发给美国（国）内各大图书馆。爷爷博士论文'程颐……思想'因系紧接在二次大战后纸张奇缺，废印制成书要求，只要求打字成书若干分发国内各大图书馆收藏，如哥伦比亚大学、哈佛大学、Princeton和华盛顿国会图书馆等，算是国内少数图书馆都有。我们家只有一、两本，存北京多多处。'" 大纲与步骤；轶事（4页）；摘要伊川文集（30页）；Forke二程日朝学者（16页）；List of Texts (10 pages);原料考证（44页）；方法（10页）；近思录（36页） (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - A.1.1.3.1 Dissertation: files of the work progress: 5）程颐哲学 -- 伊川遗书考订选辑译注 P．1-P．4 (hand writing) An Abstract; Front Page; Dedication; iii-xi Contents; xii-xvi sign, Abbreviations and Explanatory Notes; P.1 Introduction - P.313; Appendices A-D (24 pages); Continued P.1 – P. 59; Bibliography (12 pages) (Box 2, Folder 2-4)
    - A.1.1.4 "Notes on the Minchia People: I. Size of the Minchia Population; II. Area of their Habitat; III. Possible Ethnological Origin of the People; IV. Some Peculiar Characteristics of their Culture; V. Relation with Han; VI. Present Economic Life", 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Xiuying's hand copied version, with a hand copied map (8 pages)
    - A.1.1.5 "The Call from the Border Tribes", 1941 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Photocopy from The Chinese Recorder, April,1941, P.183-189）
    - A1.1.6 "Time and Eternity", 1950 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Original hand copy version, (first page written by Y.C.; P. 2 - P. 7 copied by Xiuying) Typed version: Xiuying's Note: "1950年七月初（？）从美国回国路经香港，被请在圣公会座堂会晚祷讲稿。" (4 pages); Photocopy (4 pages)
  - Writings in Chinese
    - A.1.2.1．"Correspondence with Xu Baoqian"《与徐宝谦通讯》，载《真理与生命》1933年1月七卷四期 （*复印件） (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - A.1.2.2 "Ways forward for Christianity in the new China"《新中国基督教的前进道路》，载《 新观察》第一卷第八期1950年/天风1950年10月28日（？）（*复印件） (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - A.1.2.3 "On some photographs of Comrade Xin Xinhai"《关于冼星海同志的几张相片》，载《人民音乐》，1985年第七期（封二3张照片，第33页文章黄秀英整理）（*人民音乐原件1本，*复印件1份） (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - A.1.2.4 "On Dante and the Inferno in the Divine Comedy" 《但丁及其"神曲·地狱篇"》，载《金陵神学誌》1986年（复）第四期 P42-55蔡詠春遗作、谢雪如整理 (原作于1964年，1985年12月整理) *《金陵神学誌》（*原件2本）, 1964, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - A.1.2.5 "On Dante's critique of the Middle Ages in his Divine Comedy"《但丁和"神曲"对中世纪的批判》，载《吉林大学社会科学学报》1987年第6期P26-33。 （*《吉林大学社会科学学报》原件1本，*复印件1份） (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Translations
    - A.1.3.1 "Issues on Ethnic Minorities" 少数民族问题等翻译稿多篇 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - A.1.3.1 "Issues on Ethnic Minorities" 少数民族问题等翻译稿多篇 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Chinese translation of The Christian Occupation of China, A general Survey of the Numerical Strength and Geographical Distribution of the Christian Forces in China made by the Special Committee on Survey and Occupation China Continuation Committee, 1918-1921 (3 volumes), 1985 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - "Episode of Revolutionary Life (1903-1908)" - translated from Russian into Chinese, 1956 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Notes and Manuscripts
    - Researches on Christianity
      - A.1.4.1.1 Notes from Hong Weilian's Lectures on the History of Christianity Sept 1934- June 1935 《基督教史演讲笔记细钞》洪煨莲教授讲，蔡詠春笔记Sep.1934-June 1935年 第一段：罗马帝国内基督教之崛起（Rise of Christianity in the Roman Empire） Maps copied by Tsai from E.W. Dow: Atlas of European History, Henry Holt Co. N.Y. 1909, Plate 3: Rome in and Beyond Italy; The spread of Christianity Down to 180 A.D. Drawn by Adolph Harnack 罗马帝国 I 引言； II 罗马史纲；III 安敦皇帝；罗马政府与基督教关系史料 （封面、地图、笔记单面记录共33页） *原件 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - A.1.4.1.2 "Outline in the History of Christian Thought (1950-1951)", 214 pp. 1950-1951 基督教思想史教学提纲（？）History of Christianity 1950-51 学生研读书目 1951-1952年度基督教思想史计划 基督教思想史1951-1952年度试题（温习问题） 1951春学期基督教思想史第一次小考题目 第二次月考温习题目 第一课 第二讲 Bibliography 第一章 耶稣与门生 第二章使徒保罗 第三章约翰与Ignatuis 唯物论者 使徒时代教父 谱教者 二世纪末 Montanism 之发生：（4年前基督复临教派）; Clement of Alexandria Origen 185-254 The Monarchians 东西教会独一论者们 三一论之争辩 尼西亚大会 基督的位格 西罗马基督教思想——从Tertullian 到 Gregory the Great 摩尼教 St. Augustine354-430 A.D. Anselm 1033-1109 Thomas Aquinas 1225-1274 Martin Luther 1483-1546 John Calvin Schleiermacher 1768-1834 从基督教的角度看共产主义（Tiran Nersoyan: A Christian Approach to Communism） （*原件，蔡詠春自己装订成一册，共214页） (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.1.3．Reflections on Teaching and Research in the Post-1956 era: 1956年以后对教学或科研的考虑 1）Outlines of Lectures on how Imperailists used Christianity in their aggression against China (from the Opium War to the present) 帝国主义利用基督教侵华史（鸦片战争到现代）讲课提纲（计划1957年完成初稿开课）（共4页）； 2）Outline on Jingjiao大纲—景教（共4页） 3）Literature on Jingjiao景教的文献（共3页） 4）Propagation of Jingjiao in the Tang Dynasty唐代景教传教概况（共4页） 5）First draft第一次稿（共3页） 6）Second draft第二次稿（1957。5。14）（共9页） 7）On the spread of Protestantism in China关于新教传入中国的几个问题 （共7页） 8）Teachings of Nestorianism 聂派的教义（共3页） （*原件） (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - A.1.4.1.4 Notes on Studies in Christianity (1961?); Focuses on relation the impact of Imperialist aggression on China's politics 基督教研究笔记（1961?） 侵华史书目 阅读 侵华史纲目 杂记 胡绳：帝国主义与中国政治 （俄）申曼著、李金声译：帝国主义时期的宗教 马恩 （共60页另有6-7页散纸笔记） （*原件） (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - A.1.4.1.5 Notes and Comments on Wu Shiqi's "Struggle of the Chinese People against the Colonists' manipulation of religion as a means for aggression 1860-1870". 《1860至1870年中国人民反对殖民主义者利用宗教从事侵略活动的斗争》，吴时起著，蔡詠春笔记加评语（1957年春学期）（共10页） （*原件） (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - A.1.4.1.6 Bibliography of Wu Shiqi's "Struggle of the Chinese People against the Colonists' manipulation of religion as a means for aggression 1860-1870".(Spring 1957) 《1860至1870年中国人民反对殖民主义者利用宗教从事侵略活动的斗争》，吴时起著，主要参考书目；一般参考书（1957年春学期）（共2页） （*原件） (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - A.1.4.1.7 Bibliography of Foreign books on how capitalistic nations manipulate Christianity as a means for aggression against China 资本主义国家利用基督教侵略中国史外文书目 （共四百余种）（1957年9月11日交图书馆转寄国内旧书店）（共42页） （*原件） (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - A.1.4.1.8 Notes on Karl Koutsky: Foundations of Christianity 读书摘录：Karl Koutsky: Foundations of Christianity （共70页，其中最后10页，蔡詠春写了自己的"学习总结"——书评（1954/2/13） （*原件） (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - A.1.4.1.9 Excerpts from Archibald Robertson: The Origin of Christianity, London, Lawrence & Wishart, Litd.1953） 摘录：阿奇波德·罗伯逊著：《基督教的起源》，伦敦，罗伦斯·威沙特有限公司，1953年（Archibald Robertson: The Origin of Christianity, London, Lawrence & Wishart, Litd.1953）（摘录共28页）（1957/2/7长春） （*原件及此件*复印件1件） (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - A.1.4.1.10 Notes on Archibald Robertson: The Origin of Christianity, London, Lawrence & Wishart, Litd.1953） （*笔记原件）(共28页) (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - A.1.4.1.11 Comparison between Koutsky and Robertson 考茨基与罗伯逊之比较、批评 （读后感性质，共26页） （*原件） (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - A.1.4.1.12 Notes on The World Almanac 1949 读书笔记 （共20页，加一张小条，一个参考消息1964年4月7日剪报） （*原件） (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - A.1.4.1.13 On the Development of Eschatological Thinking in the Bible 《圣经》末世论思想的发展（资料）手稿，年代不详。目录2页；全文62页 （*原件及*复印件） (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
      - A.1.4.1.14 Plans for "A Short Bible", c. 1964 《圣经》文选计划（大约1964年）（英文手稿） （*复印件，共3页） (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Studies on Dante
      - A.1.4.2.1．关于但丁《神曲》研究，论文命题与纲目（1963年）：但丁《神曲》中有关《圣经》背景的几个问题（装订好，共28页） (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - A.1.4.2.2．纲目（共4页） (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - A.1.4.2.3．过渡时期的伟大诗人但丁——试论《神曲》对教育的批判和反抗，1964年7月2日写毕目录（共5页） (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - A.1.4.2.4．伟大的诗人但丁——试论《神曲》对教会的批判和反抗（提纲）1964年7月6日（共 14页） (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - A.1.4.2.5．但丁《神曲》对教会的批判和反抗 （一）总论 1964年1月25日（共34页 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - A.1.4.2.6．草稿备忘（共7页）1963/3/8 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - A.1.4.2.7．但丁——伟大过渡时代的伟大诗人（草稿共3页） (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - A.1.4.2.8．伟大的过渡时代（草稿共6页） (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - A.1.4.2.9．提纲草稿，小引——但丁在历史上的作用，经典作家评价…（共7页） (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - A.1.4.2.10．零什（共21页） (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - A.1.4.2.11．但丁政治思想的局限性（共4页） (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - A.1.4.2.12．但丁，欧洲中世纪文学作品选但丁章， 李文鏸同志口译（共26页） (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - A.1.4.2.13．但丁阶级立场分析——论点，1963/8/17（共4页） (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - A.1.4.2.14．但丁——伟大过渡时代的伟大诗人纲目1963/8/23 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - A.1.4.2.15．李尚信同志讲（西欧文学史课）但丁1963/11/12；1963/11/19（共12页） (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - A.1.4.2.16．从《神曲》对教会的批判看但丁的政治倾向性 1963/11/13 （共3页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.17．"杀彼女贼"——试论《神曲》对教会的批判（初稿大纲）1963/11/17（共4页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.18．娼妓与神车——试论但丁《神曲》对教会的态度1963/11/18（共13页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.19．"披着牧人衣服的贪狼"——试论但丁《神曲》对教会的批评1963/12/1（共4页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.20．但丁对人间爱情的肯定（共4页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.21．但丁关于爱情问题的局限性段（共2页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.22．但丁人道主义思想批判、 但丁《神曲》的总的评价1964/10/29（共13页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.23．但丁政治思想批判（补充）1964/10/29（共1页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.24．（二）但丁所依据的圣经末世论轮廓（10min.）(共5 页) (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.25．《但丁——伟大过渡时代的伟大诗人》大纲 8月20日上午（共2页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.26．（？）草稿（共6页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.27．？草稿P。50-57 "此段补头接尾，可留作独立篇章"（共7页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.28．"稿纸"（共3页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.29 但丁文艺思想的批判（共11页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.30 《神曲》中透露但丁对基督教的看法（共4页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.31 散，右下角编号，（缺P1）P2-3，（缺P4），P5-8，（缺P9），P10 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.32 政治思想批判（共2页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.33 二、但丁（批判教会）又反映了人民反教的革命情绪（共3页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.34 综合资料卡片目录（1页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.35 关于但丁对教会的批判综合资料（1页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.36 四、但丁批判教会的阶级立场和意义（共2页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.37 散稿"但丁跨在两个时代……"（共2页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.38 散稿"评价"（1页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.39 1，2，3，（东北人民大学稿纸）（1页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.40散稿"但丁批判教会在当代的意义及影响"（1页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.41 散页：只有下方"第三大段末应加一段……"（1页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.42 征求意见（周若予、尹曲、中文系薛纯华、刘存宽、王藻、李尚信徐枫等人）（共26页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.43．尹曲：《文艺复兴的历史意义》（吉林大学社会科学学报） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.44．良玉为父亲遗作《但丁和"神曲"对中世纪的批判》的发表问题写给匡亚明校长及夫人丁莹如的信，1985/8/11（共2页） (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - A.1.4.2.45．良玉为父亲遗作：《但丁极其"神曲·地狱篇"》给谢雪如的信及起草的《编者按》，1985/8/10 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Manuscripts of Translated Works
    - A.1.5.1 The Christian Occupation of China, A general Survey of the Numerical Strength and Geographical Distribution of the Christian Forces in China made by the Special Committee on Survey and Occupation China Continuation Committee, 1918-1921 ) Chapter Nine. 《中华归主》译文第九篇部分手稿：译注共209条，36页；第三册甲：中国回民基督教事业（46页）；中华基督教青年会：目次——全文（未完）共200页；？——结语（共34页）；中华归主附录己：睦谊协约宣言（共48页） （*手稿原件） (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
    - A.1.5.2 Translation of Michael Hamburger's Beethoven: Letters, Journals and Conversations 《贝多芬书信、日志、谈话》（英）迈克尔·汉伯格辑译，蔡詠春摘译（共81页） （*手稿原件） (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - A.1.5.3 Excerpts on Beethoven: 《贝多芬资料摘译》蔡詠春摘译，摘自： 一，《贝多芬书信集》（德）A·C·卡利舍尔编（全集）；（英）J· S· 谢德洛克译英；（英）A· 伊格尔菲尔德——赫尔选辑。伦敦，1926。 二，《贝多芬庄严弥撒总谱·前言》。 三，（英）A ·W ·塞耶著《贝多芬传》。 四，（德）W ·里茨勒著：《贝多芬传》。 五，（法）保罗·兰多米著《音乐史》"贝多芬"章。 （共36页）（缺页P16-20） （*手稿原件） (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - A.1.5.4 Beethoven's Fantasia Op80 贝多芬《合唱幻想曲》（作品80）歌词，（共2页） （*手稿原件） (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Other notes
    - Notes added 2010 (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Biographical Documentation, 1945-1985; Series II
  - Re. work at Huidian Hospital
    - A.2.1 1945 Huidian Hospital Donations Accounts 1945 年惠滇医院善鄰金收入登记表（5页） 信件（金兆和来信、1945/5/23蔡詠春（1页） 写给美国朋友的感谢信打字稿（共2页） 情况记录（苏兆民、段文宇、邹维亚之弟、申凌宵等，共5页） 帐目（共2页） （*原件) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Address books
    - A.2.2.1 棕色Rev. Y.C.Ts'ai (ETS 99 Brattle St. Cambridge 38, Mass)（*原件） (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - A.2.2.2 蓝色"爷爷生日快乐，小青" （*原件） (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Diaries
    - A.2.3 Table of Contents of Diary 1952 年笔记目录2 页（*原件） (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - A.2.4.1 1952年小小的日记本（*原件） (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - A.2.4.2 1962年7月30日—1963年1月30日（*原件）, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - A.2.4.3 1966年1月—1966年8月（*原件） (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - A.2.4.4 1966年8月14日-1966年12月31日（*原件） (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - A.2.4.5 1967年1月1日-3月31日（*原件） (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - A.2.4.6 1967年4月-8月31日（*原件） (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - A.2.4.7 1967年9月8日-12月29日（*原件） (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - A.2.4.8 1968年1月1日-1969年8月8日（*原件） A.2.4.9 1969年3月-1969年6月（*原件）, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - A.2.4.10 1975年5月23日-1976年3月13日（后半本有1967/5/31-1968/1/26）（*原件）, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - A.2.4.11 1980年2月6日-3月2日（*原件） (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - A.2.4.12 黄皮日记本1980年4月3日-1983年5月8日（*原件）, 1980-1983 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - A.2.4.13 Union Theological Seminary Record (1946-47,1947-48 first semester) Original version (1 page), 1946-1948 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Drafts of Letters
    - A.2.5.1 1950年4月21日告别信(Farewell Letter)(打字稿1页) （*原件及*复印件1件） (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - A.2.5.2 1973年5月4日—1973年8月16日（"作业"本子）（*原件） (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - A.2.5.3 1973年8月21日-1974年1月20日（"作业"本子）（*原件）, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - A.2.5.4 1976年4月-1977年9月18日（"备课笔记"本子）（*原件）, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - A.2.5.5 1965年11月14日-1982年6月29/30日（绿色日记本"江山如此多娇"）（*原件）, 1965-1982 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - A.2.5.6 绿色日记本（"江山如此多娇"）中夹的零碎信稿等： ①1977年6月30日给厦门市公共交通汽车公司革委会负责同志信及附件（共3页） ②1977年12月13日给多多信的补充（共1页） ③1978年11月24日致谢雪如信 ③1979年培元中学建校七十五周年庆祝活动日程表、蔡詠春题词底稿、抄杜甫诗《赠六处士》（共3页） ④1980年（？）致谢永崇信 ⑤？（1980？）年12月5日致友三同学信 ⑥1981年3月19日致Hugh Barbour信 ⑦1982年7月27日致林心铿信 ⑧？（无日期）抄郭沫若游泉州诗（开元寺勒石） ⑨？（无日期）关于为（蔡詠春的）母亲骨灰安葬事宜给（？）的信、（智）推托理由、母亲骨灰盒安葬帐目（共3页） ⑩便条记事二则：国务院上访处问宗院归何关，政策未落实到底，工资工龄恢复原职别；前金同志来时，谈我们（退休证上写的"未定级"问题）的定级问题…。 ⑾1978年3月2日给邓炎昌信稿（2面） (12）1978年6月13日致香港（？）德坤学长（介绍吴锦东）（共3面） (13）1978年11月15日秀英给凃碧波、蔡镏生信（关于秀英恢复学衔）（共2页） (14）1967年吉林大学造反委员会给蔡詠春的通知 （*原件14份） (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - A.2.5.7 Correspondence on the establishing of Xiamen University ①1979年3月9日致蔡启瑞（共1页）②1979年5月19日曾书记和诸位领导（共2页） ③1979年3月6日关于厦大基建规划的几点意见（共5页）另外一份第5页写有："这里第（十）条定稿时未用，留备参考。"（共1页） ④1979年3月10日致刘正坤信（共1页） （*原手稿复写件） (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - A.2.5.8 Correspondence on the design of Quanzhou Huaqiao University ①1979年2月4日给蔡馏生信复写本（共7页）另加妈妈写的说明（共1页） ②1979年4月16日林蒲田来信（共1页） ③1979年5月27日汪大铭来信（共1页） ④1979年4月29日给汪大铭信，以及附建议一份（共3页） ⑤1979年5月12日给汪大铭信，以及附件："关于侨生教育的几点初步意见"（共9页） ⑥1979年9月18日汪大铭来信（共1页） ⑦1979年12月26日汪大铭来信（共1页） ⑧散页：华侨大学图、关于校容小组初步设想（共3页） ⑨《华侨大学简讯》1979年5月28日（6月17日校对毕） ⑩有关校园美化剪报：《参考消息》1978/11/28；《人民日报》1978/12/7；1978/12/13；1979/1/4第六版；《参考消息》1979/2/26；《人民日报》1979/3/14；《光明日报》1980/1/13（共7页） （*原手稿复写件及原件）, 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - A.2.5.9 Correspondence on Peiyuan Secondary School ①1979年8月11日培元中学校长办公室来信（共1页） ②？（无日期）詠春回信（共1页） ③1979年10月12日詠春回信（共1页） ④1979年7月7日培元1董事会筹备组来信（共1页） （*原件） (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - A.2.5.10 Letter to Cai Liusheng August 25 1982 1982年8月25日致蔡镏生信（共1页） （*复印件） (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - A.2.5.11 Messages between Cai Yongchun and Huang Xiuying during his hospitalization from Sept to October 29 1982 1982年9月-10月29日詠春住院期间与秀英之间的便条。（詠春共69张；秀英共12张）（*原件） (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - A.2.5.12 Letter to Comrade Liu Ruxin on May 5 1983, nineteen days before Cai's death 1983年5月5日刘如新同志信（注意：此信写于詠春去世前19天！） （*原件） (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - A.2.5.13 Letter from Huang Xiuying to Ren Yongkang on the whereabouts of the documents surrendered to the Government in 1952 (August 15 1985) 1985年8月15日秀英给任永康信，问1952年上交材料去向（1页） （*信稿原件） (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - A.2.5.14 Reply from the Alumni Department to Huang Xiuying (September 4 1985) 1985年9月4日校友联络组回秀英信 （*原件） (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with authorities
    Regarding political status, retirement, accommodation, food coupons, and medical benefits
    - A.2.6 关于落实政策、退休、户口、住房、粮票、公费医疗等信件 （1）1972年吉林大学革委会、外文系等（共10页）（*原件） （2）1973年吉林大学革委会、外文系等（共7页）（*原件） （3）1974年吉林大学革委会、外文系；厦门大学等（共7页）（*原件） （4）1974年6月13日蔡詠春致吉林大学革委会（共2页）（*原件） （5）1974年蔡红玉致厦门大学、吉林大学信；吉林大学给红玉信（抄件） 红玉给爸爸妈妈信（*原件与抄件共10页） （6）1975年吉林大学介绍信、来信（共2页）（*原件） （7）1973、1975年吉林大学外文系李青信三封（共4页）（*原件） (8) 1979年4月19日吉林大学人事处《关于蔡詠春同志调查报告》（*打印件） （9）1979年4月19日吉林大学人事处《关于黄秀英同志调查报告》（*打印件）, 1972-1979 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Medical records
    - 本人医疗记录材料 （1）长春病历和病情记录。共16份（*原件） （2）茂名、广州、湛江。共7份（*原件） （3）厦门。共6份（*原件） （4）上海。共1份（*原件） （5）北京。共12份（*原件） （6）各医院诊断。共8份（*原件） （7）医疗杂记（本子）（*愿件） （8）剪报2份（*原件） （9）1978-1979疗养日记（*原件） （10）1980-1981．7疗养日记（*原件） （11）1981．8——1982。12疗养日记（*原件） （12）1983年疗养日记（*原件） （13）1982年在北京市第六医院住院记录（*原件1份） (14) 北京中医学院病理解剖报告（*原件）(boxes 6 and 7), 1978-1982 (Box 6)
    - 本人医疗记录材料 （1）长春病历和病情记录。共16份（*原件） （2）茂名、广州、湛江。共7份（*原件） （3）厦门。共6份（*原件） （4）上海。共1份（*原件） （5）北京。共12份（*原件） （6）各医院诊断。共8份（*原件） （7）医疗杂记（本子）（*愿件） （8）剪报2份（*原件） （9）1978-1979疗养日记（*原件） （10）1980-1981．7疗养日记（*原件） （11）1981．8——1982。12疗养日记（*原件） （12）1983年疗养日记（*原件） （13）1982年在北京市第六医院住院记录（*原件1份） (14) 北京中医学院病理解剖报告（*原件）(boxes 6 and 7) (Box 7)
  - Autobiographical information自传材料
    - 1．自传， 1956 （共26页，未完）（*复写原件) (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 2．与佟冬副校长谈话 1957/10/2下午。10月4日整理（*原件） (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 3．进一步检查错误，追溯根源 1957/10/9（共16页）（*原件） (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 4．彻底转变立场，迎接思想工作上的大跃进事业1958/6 （共47页）（*自己装订的本子复写原件） (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 5．学习总结 1960/8/15（共13页）（*复写原件） (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 6．？（无日期，估计是1960年）（分订为两小本，分别为20页，16页）（*原件） (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 7．自传，1968/5/18 （1）P7—P75；（2）P76-P92；（缺P93-P100）；（3）P101-P132 （*自己装订的本子，共3本原件） (Box 7, Folder 4)